Guide to the Jason Parker Thomson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jason Parker Thomson papers
1853-1938
1896-1938
MS 1158
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(3 boxes)
The Jason Parker Thomson papers consist of case files and notes for a small portion of Thomson's legal career in New Haven, Connecticut and personal papers such as correspondence, family papers, financial and legal records, and memorabilia. Many of the legal files concern estate settlements, property in New Haven, and legal work done for family members. Personal papers relate to Thomson's affiliation with various civic organizations, the management of personal property, and his financial fortunes in the face of the depression.
Thomson, Jason Parker, 1853-1946
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jason Parker Thomson, 1930-1938. Additional material received through Ray Sanborn's office in 1950.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Jason Parker Thomson Papers consist of case files and notes for a small portion of Thomson's legal career in New Haven, Connecticut, and personal papers such as correspondence, family papers, financial and legal records, and memorabilia. Many of the legal files concern estate settlements, property in New Haven, and legal work done for family members. Personal papers relate to Thomson's affiliation with various civic organizations, the management of personal property, and his financial fortunes in the face of the depression.
Jason Parker Thomson gave a portion of these papers to the Yale Library between 1930 and 1938. Additional papers were found in Ray Sanborn's office in 1950 and were then transferred to Manuscripts and Archives.
Biographical / Historical
Jason Parker Thomson, LL.B. 1884
Born December 28, 1853, in New Haven, Conn.
Died January 24, 1946, in New Haven, Conn.
Father, Edgar Teed Thomson of Woodbury, Conn.; founder Tuttle, Morehouse & Taylor, book and job printers, binders, and stationers, New Haven; son of Bela and Sylvia (Teed) Thomson of Litchfield, Conn. Mother, Elizabeth Palmer (Shelley) Thomson; daughter of Orrin and Elizabether (Palmer) Shelley of Guilford, Conn.
Lancasterian School, New Haven, and Westville (Conn.) Academy; pony express rider, Cass County, Mo., 1868-70; attended Yale Law School 1882-84 (LL.B 1884; member Kent Club); assistant to Judge Lynde Harrison (LL.B. 1860) and Judge Levi N. Blydenburg, New Haven, 1884-96; lawyer in New Haven, specializing in probate work, 1897 until retirement in 1926; resided in New Haven, and Miami, Fla.; member Second Company, Governor's Foot Guard (historian of the company and author; History of Second Company, Governor's Foot Guard, 1899 ), New Haven County Bar Association, Masonic order, and St. James Church (Episcopal), New Haven.
Married June 18, 1891, in Brewster, N.Y.; Margaret Louise, daugher of Mathias Leviticus and Estelle (Armstrong) Darton. Children: Gertrude Darton (Yale Graduate School 1914-17), the wife of Samuel Alford Guilford; and Jason Parker, Jr. Mrs. Thomson died August 4, 1936.
Death due to generalized arteriosclerosis. Buried in Fair Haven Union Cemetery, New Haven. Survived by children.
( Yale University Obituary Record, 1945-1947, page 204)
Law; New Haven (Conn.); Lawyers; Thomson, Jason Parker, 1853-1946
- Inventory
  - Legal Papers
    - American Surety Company, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ammann, Gottfried, estate, 1910, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bradley, John. H., 1903-04 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Brown, Mabel Thomas, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dingwell, Catherine, estate, 1926-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Frederick, Edward G. and Helen B., 1927-28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Griswold, Florence Thomson, 1935-36 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Holaday, Albert E., 1933-34 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 9)
    - James, Annie E., estate, 1899-1902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Junior Scouts of Connecticut, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ladies Home Missionary Society of the First Church in New Haven vs. Frederick B. Smith et. ux. et. al., 1901-02 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lewis, Emm, 1917-18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mendles vs. Moffet, 1899-1901 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mower family, [ca.1896-1931] (Box 1, Folder 15 - 17)
    - New Haven Armory Commission, 1927-28 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Palmer, Caroline et al. vs. Josephine Neubauer, 1903-04 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Smith, Clarence V., Trustee vs. Jason P. Thomson, 1914-16 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Stone, Amanda, estate, [ca.1900-07] (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Thompson, Sarah, 1901-02 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous legal papers, [ca.1892-1936] (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous legal notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Personal papers
    - Family correspondence and notes on family history, [ca.1872-1937] (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, general, 1889-1938 (Box 3, Folder 26 - 30)
    - Memorabilia, personal and family, [ca.1853-1936] (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Financial and legal papers, [ca.1891-1938] (Box 3, Folder 32 - 33)